April 9, 1940. Under the code name "Operation Weserübung",
Nazi Germany invades Denmark and Norway. On the strategic level,
Denmark is important for Germany as a platform for operations in Norway.
In Norway, Germany is seeking to secure naval bases to use against the British fleet.
in the North Sea and ensure vital shipments of iron ore from neutral Sweden,
on which Nazi Germany depends. Although the invasion of Denmark lasts
less than six hours and constitutes the shortest military campaign carried out by the Germans
During the war, Norway surrendered to Hitler just two months later, on June 10, 1940.
On February 1, 1942, the Germans appointed a minister president whose puppet government,
collaborationist and pro-Nazi, will participate in Germany's war efforts and expel the
Jews from the country to concentration camps in Nazi-occupied Poland.
His name, which would become synonymous with "collaborator" or "traitor," is Vidkun Quisling.
Vidkun Abraham Lauritz Jonssøn Quisling was born on July 18, 1887 in Fyresdal,
in southern Norway. His father, Jon Lauritz Quisling, was a Lutheran minister and genealogist,
and his mother, Anna Caroline Bang, came from a wealthy family in Grimstad, Norway.
In 1905, 18-year-old Vidkun Quisling entered the War College. Of the 250 cadets,
He obtained the highest score on the entrance exams, known for their difficulty.
After graduating from War College, Quisling entered the Military Academy to continue his studies.
his career in the military. Vidkun Quisling graduated with the highest grades in the history of
the Academy since its foundation in 1817, and the King of Norway rewarded him by inviting him to an audience.
In 1911, Quisling joined the Norwegian Army General Staff. Three years later,
On July 28, 1914, World War I began. During the war,
Norway remained neutral. Quisling hated the peace movement, although the high cost
The human nature of the war moderated his views. In March 1918, he was sent to Russia as
attaché of the Norwegian legation in Petrograd. Although dismayed by
the living conditions he experienced, Quisling concluded that "the Bolsheviks
"They have an extraordinarily strong influence on Russian society" and marveled
how Leon Trotsky had managed to mobilize the forces of the Red Army so well.
He stated that, on the other hand, by granting too many rights to the Russian people, the Provisional Government
Alexander Kerensky's Russian government had brought about its own downfall. When the legation was withdrawn
In December 1918, Quisling became the Norwegian army's expert on Russian affairs.
In September 1919, Quisling left Norway to become an intelligence officer in the
his country's delegation in Helsinki, Finland, a position that combined diplomacy and politics
and in January 1922 arrived in the Ukrainian capital, Kharkiv, to assist with relief efforts
League of Nations humanitarian there. In August of that same year, he married the
Russian Alexandra Andreevna Voronina. Apparently, there was no romantic relationship between the two.
and it is believed that Quisling simply seemed to want to lift the young woman out of poverty by providing her with a
Norwegian passport and financial security. Shortly after, he met Maria Vasiljevna
Pasetchnikova, a Ukrainian ten years his junior. The couple acted as if they were married,
He claimed that Alexandra was his daughter and celebrated their wedding anniversary.
However, his stay in Russia had the greatest impact on his thinking.
Quisling's politician. Quisling called his political philosophy "Universitism." The goal
was to develop a collective consciousness for global unity, transferring consciousness
from the individual level to the national level. Over time, Universism acquired a component
racial, as it incorporated the belief in Nordic racial superiority. He claimed that the path
Towards world unity would only be achieved under Nordic leadership, working against the Jews.
Quisling returned to Norway permanently in 1929. He served as Minister of Defence
Norwegian between 1931 and 1933 as a member of the Agrarian Party. When the Agrarian Party refused to
appoint Quisling as leader, he left to form his own political party. In May
In 1933, he co-founded the political party Nasjonal Samling (National Unity). Quisling also became
in the party's forer (or leader). The party's platform was based on four principles:
- a corporatist view of society - an emphasis on nationalism and Christianity
- State paternalism - and economic self-sufficiency.
However, the Nasjonal Samling was unsuccessful in the elections. In the parliamentary elections
In the 1933 Norwegian elections, the party obtained 2.2% of the vote. In 1936, the last elections held
Before the outbreak of World War II, only 1.8% was obtained. None of
These results were enough to obtain a seat in the Storting, the unicameral Norwegian Parliament.
Furthermore, the decline in party membership created many problems for Quisling,
especially financial. For years he suffered financial difficulties and relied on his inheritance,
while an increasing number of his paintings,
acquired at low prices in post-revolutionary Russia, were discovered as
copies when he tried to sell them. His collection numbered about 200 paintings,
including works supposedly by Rembrandt, Goya, Cézanne and numerous other masters.
However, sometimes even the originals did not achieve as much as Quisling had hoped. Vidkun and
His brother Arne sold a painting by Frans Hals for only four thousand dollars, believing it to be
a copy and not the fifty thousand dollar work of art they once believed it to be,
only to see it reclassified as original and revalued at one hundred thousand dollars.
In 1939, Quisling turned his attention to Norway's preparations for the impending
European war, which, according to him, involved a drastic increase in the country's defense spending
to ensure its neutrality. Meanwhile, he gave lectures entitled "The Problem
"Jewish in Norway" and supported Adolf Hitler in what seemed to be a future conflict in progress.
Despite condemning the Night of Broken Glass or Kristallnacht, as it is known in German,
series of coordinated violent riots against Jews throughout Nazi Germany
and the newly incorporated territories, which occurred on November 9 and 10, 1938,
sent the German leader a congratulations on his fiftieth birthday, thanking him
for "saving Europe from Bolshevism and Jewish domination." Quisling also maintained that,
If an Anglo-Russian alliance made neutrality impossible, Norway would have to "join"
Germany". Invited to the country in the summer of 1939, he began a tour of several Teutonic cities and
Danish. It was especially well received in Germany, which pledged funds to improve
the image of Nasjonal Samling in Norway and thus spread pro-Nazi sentiment.
At the beginning of World War II in 1939, Norway, like all of Scandinavia,
acquired new strategic importance for Germany. Erich Raeder, commander of the navy
German between 1939 and 1943, was concerned with maintaining German naval access to the North Sea
and the Atlantic Ocean via naval bases on the Norwegian coast. In December 1939,
First Raeder and then Hitler met with Quisling. The Führer was impressed in terms
generals. Quisling suggested that the British were planning to invade Norway to satisfy their
own strategic needs. Alarmed, Germany began planning Operation
Weserübung, the invasion of Denmark and Norway. The German entry into Norway,
under the command of General Nikolaus von Falkenhorst, began on April 9, 1940.
That same day, as the German offensive began, Quisling attempted to seize power in
the world's first radio coup d'état. He announced to the Norwegian people that they should welcome,
Instead of resisting the German advance, he also announced a new government and proclaimed himself
new head of state. Two hours later, Quisling repeated his radio announcement. This time,
He warned that any refusal to cooperate with the new government would, henceforth, lead to
the most serious consequences for those involved.
Quisling then reached the height of his political power. On Hitler's orders, Curt Bräuer,
Germany's representative in Norway during the invasion, demanded that King Haakon appoint him
head of a new government, thus ensuring a peaceful transition of power and giving validity
legal to the occupation. However, Haakon rejected this demand. He went further in a meeting with
his cabinet, declaring to ministers that he could not appoint Quisling as prime minister because
Neither the people nor the Norwegian Parliament trusted him. He made it clear that he would abdicate rather than appoint
a government headed by Quisling. In response, the government voted unanimously in favor of the
the king's position. He formally advised him not to appoint any Quisling-led government
and urged the people to continue their resistance. Having lost his popular support, Quisling ceased
be useful to Hitler. Germany withdrew its support for its rival government, preferring instead to form
its own independent governing commission. On April 15, 1940, the Nazi leadership
forced him to resign. Thus, Quisling's coup only lasted six days and his reputation,
both nationally and internationally, plummeted, presenting him as a traitor and a failure.
Norway fell to Germany on June 19, 1940.
and the king and Prime Minister Johan Nygaardsvold went into exile in London.
On April 24, 1940, Hitler appointed Josef Terboven as Reich Commissioner for the
Occupied Norwegian Territories. General Von Falkenhorst, who had planned and
Commanded the German invasion of Denmark and Norway in 1940, he maintained military control.
Furthermore, all political parties, except Quisling's Nasjonal Samling,
were outlawed. As leader of the Nasjonal Samling, Quisling held the leadership of the
cabinet under Terboven. In early 1942, Terboven appointed him Minister President of
a National Government. With all this, Norway was, in essence, a puppet state under German control.
During the summer of 1942, Quisling lost all ability to influence public opinion.
public by trying to force children to join the youth organization Nasjonal Samlings
Ungdomsfylking, inspired by the Hitler Youth. This measure led to the resignation
massive dismissal of teachers from their guild and clergy from their posts, in addition to large-scale civil unrest
scale. His attempt to accuse Bishop Eivind Berggrav proved equally controversial,
even among their German allies. Quisling hardened his stance, declaring to the Norwegians
who would accept the new imposed regime "whether they liked it or not." On May 1, 1942,
The German High Command noted that "organized resistance against Quisling had begun" and,
As a result, Norway's peace talks with Germany stalled.
On August 11, 1942, Hitler postponed any further peace negotiations until the
end of the war. To top it all off, for the first time he was forbidden to write letters directly to Hitler.
Quisling believed that the only way to regain Hitler's respect was to recruit volunteers to
the now faltering German war effort. Following the German defeat at Stalingrad in February 1943,
committed Norway unconditionally to German plans for total war.
Approximately 15,000 Norwegians volunteered to fight on the Nazi side,
and of the 6,000 sent into action as part of the Germanic SS,
Most of them were sent to the Eastern Front. Germanic SS was the collective name given to
the paramilitary and political organizations established in parts of
Germany-occupied Europe between 1939 and 1945 under the auspices of the German SS.
One of Quisling's first acts as Prime Minister was to reinstate
the so-called Jewish paragraph of the Norwegian Constitution. This paragraph, repealed in 1851,
prevented Jewish immigration to Norway. Between October and November 1942, Quisling signed a
series of laws that allowed the arrest of all Norwegian Jewish men, the confiscation of
all property and assets of said community and the registration of all Norwegian Jews.
There were approximately 2,100 Jews in Norway at the time of the German invasion.
Among them were about 350 German and Austrian refugees who had sought refuge
of Nazi Germany. A month after the mass arrest of Jewish men, Nazi officers who
working with Quisling's Nasjonal Samling they began arresting women and children. Following
pre-developed plans, the Norwegian police arrested Jews throughout Norway and
took them to Oslo for deportation to Germany. The first deportation of 532 Jews left
from Oslo on 26 November 1942. Another 158 were deported on 25 February 1943,
followed by transfers of smaller groups. In total, 772 Norwegian Jews were deported
from the Norwegian capital to Germany. From Oslo, local Jews were sent by ship to
the German port city of Stettin, present-day Szczecin in Poland. They were then transported by
train to Auschwitz, where most were gassed immediately upon arrival. However,
34 Norwegian Jews, all men, ultimately survived to witness the end of the war.
Fortunately, many Jews received advance warning of the raids by the
Norwegian police and members of the resistance. As a result, many Norwegian Jews, about 1,000,
They escaped to neutral Sweden with the help of the resistance, and many others went into hiding.
After the deportation of the Jews, Germany deported Norwegian officers and eventually attempted
deport students from the University of Oslo. Even Hitler was outraged by
the scale of the arrests. Quisling was involved in a similar debacle earlier
of 1944 by imposing compulsory military service on members of the Hirden,
which caused several members to resign to avoid being recruited.
The Hirden were a uniformed paramilitary organization during the occupation of Norway
by Nazi Germany, based on the same model as the German SS.
On January 20, 1945, Quisling made what would be his last trip to visit Hitler.
He promised Norwegian support in the final phase of the war if Germany accepted a peace agreement that
remove Norwegian affairs from German intervention. This proposal arose from the fear that,
As German forces withdrew south through Norway, the government
occupation would have to fight to maintain control in the north of the country. To the horror
of the Quisling regime, the Nazis opted for a scorched earth policy in northern
Norway, even going so far as to shoot Norwegian civilians who refused to evacuate the region.
The period was also marked by increasing civilian casualties caused by bombing.
allies and the growing resistance to the government within occupied Norway.
The meeting with the German leader was unsuccessful and, when he was asked to
sign the execution order for thousands of Norwegian "saboteurs", Quisling refused,
an act of defiance that so enraged Terboven that, following Hitler's orders, he abandoned
the negotiations. Recounting the events of the trip to a friend, Quisling burst into tears,
convinced that the Nazi refusal to sign a peace agreement would seal his reputation as a traitor.
Adolf Hitler committed suicide on April 30, 1945. Privately, Quisling had long accepted
time that National Socialism would be defeated and, on May 7, ordered the police not to offer
armed resistance to the Allied advance, except in self-defense or against declared members
of the Norwegian resistance movement. That same day, Germany announced its unconditional surrender,
which made Quisling's position untenable. A realist, he met with the military leaders
of the resistance the next day to discuss how he would be arrested. Quisling stated that,
While he didn't want to be treated like a common criminal, he didn't want a
preferential treatment compared to their colleagues at Nasjonal Samling. He argued that
could have kept his forces fighting to the bitter end, but had opted to
ensure a peaceful transition to avoid turning Norway into a battlefield.
On 9 May 1945, Quisling and his ministers surrendered to the police. He was taken to the
Cell 12 at Møllergata 19, the main police station in Oslo. The cell contained
a small table, a sink and a hole in the wall where a toilet bucket used to be.
After ten weeks under police surveillance to prevent suicide attempts,
He was transferred to Akershus Fortress and awaited trial as part of the legal purge.
The trial began on 20 August 1945. Quisling was charged with murder,
embezzlement, theft, and other crimes. The most worrying for Quisling was the accusation of
conspire with Hitler to invade and occupy Norway. In court, he argued that
He acted in the best interests of Norway and always with the aim of restoring Norwegian independence.
He distorted the truth on several occasions and most of his truthful statements earned him
little support in the country as a whole, where he continued to be almost universally despised.
In the last days of the trial, Quisling's health suffered,
largely due to the amount of medical tests he underwent,
and his defense faltered. The prosecution's final statement attributed responsibility to the
Final Solution in Norway to Quisling, based on the testimony of German officials.
On September 10, 1945, when the verdict was announced, Quisling was found guilty.
on all but a few minor charges and was therefore sentenced to death.
After testifying in several trials against members of Nasjonal Samling,
Quisling was executed by firing squad at Akershus Fortress
On October 24, 1945, at 2:40 a.m. His last words
Before being shot, they said: "I am condemned unjustly and I die innocent." After his death,
His body was cremated, leaving the ashes to be buried in Fyresdal, his hometown.
Quisling's residence, Villa Grande, which he called "Gimlé",
a name taken from Norse mythology, today houses the Norwegian Centre for Studies
on the Holocaust and Minorities, a research, education and documentation center
in Oslo focused on the Holocaust, other genocides, extremism, anti-Semitism,
Hate speech and the situation of minorities in contemporary societies.
On May 8, 1945, the day before he surrendered to the police, Quisling said the following:
"I know that the Norwegian people have condemned me to death and that the easiest thing for me would be
take my own life. But I want history to dictate its own verdict. Believe me, within
In ten years I will have become another Saint Olaf." However, he was wrong. While the saga of Saint
Olaf became a central element of the national identity and is a symbol of the
Norwegian independence and pride, Vidkun Quisling has become
one of the most infamous traitors in history due to his collaboration with Nazi Germany.
Outside Norway, the word "quisling" has outlived the memory of Vidkun himself and
has become synonymous with "traitor," a usage that began during the war.
The term "quisling" continues to be applied to political figures who collaborate with foreign powers,
especially with invading forces. However, it is also used as a term
general term to refer to a traitor. Thus, his betrayal of Norway to Germany
has turned his name into a label for all collaborators and traitors.
No tears were shed for Vidkun Quisling.
Thanks for watching World History Channel. Don't forget to like it,
Subscribe and click the notification bell so you don't miss out
our next videos. Thanks. See you next time on the channel.